Chapter 96.
The triworks.
Besides her hoisted boats, an American whaler is outwardly distinguished by her
triworks. She presents the curious anomaly of the most solid masonry
joining with oak and hemp in constituting the completed ship. It is
as if from the open field a brick kiln were transported to her planks.
The triworks are planted between the formast and the main mast, the most
roomy part of the deck. The timbers beneath are of a peculiar strength,
fitted to sustain the weight of an almost solid mass of brick and mortar,
some 10 ft by 8 square and five in height. The foundation does not
penetrate the deck, but the masonry is firmly secured to the surface by
ponderous knees of iron bracing it on all sides and screwing it down to the
timbers. On the flanks, it is cased with wood and at top completely covered by a
large sloping battened hatchway.
Removing this hatch we expose the great tripods, two in number and each of
several barrels capacity.
When not in use, they are kept remarkably clean. Sometimes they are
polished with soap stone and sand till they shine within like silver punch
bowls. During the night watches, some cynical old sailors will crawl into them
and coil themselves away there for a nap. While employed in polishing them,
one man in each pot side by side, many confidential communications are carried
on over the iron lips. It is a place also for profound mathematical
meditation. It was in the lefthand tripod of the peekquad, with the soap
stone diligently circling around me, that I was first indirectly struck by
the remarkable fact that in geometry all bodies gliding along the cyclloid, my
soap stone, for example, will descend from any point in precisely the same time.
Removing the fireboard from the front of the triworks, the bare masonry of that
side is exposed, penetrated by the two iron mouths of the furnaces directly
underneath the pots. These mouths are fitted with heavy doors of iron. The
intense heat of the fire is prevented from communicating itself to the deck by
means of a shallow reservoir extending under the entire enclosed surface of the
works by a tunnel inserted at the rear.
This reservoir is kept replenished with water as fast as it evaporates. There
are no external chimneys. They open direct from the rear wall. And here, let
us go back for a moment.
It was about 9:00 at night that the Peekquad's triworks were first started
on this present voyage. It belonged to Stub to oversee the business. Already
there off hatch then, and starter. You cook, fire the works. This was an easy
thing, for the carpenter had been thrusting his shavings into the furnace
throughout the passage. Here be it said that in a whailing voyage the first fire
in the triworks has to be fed for a time with wood. After that no wood is used
except as a means of quick ignition to the staple fuel. In a word, after being
tried out, the crisp, shriveled blubber, now called scraps or fritters, still
contains considerable of its anxious properties. These fritters feed the
flames like a plethoric burning martyr or self-consuming misenthrope. Once
ignited, the whale supplies his own fuel and burns by his own body. Would that he
consumed his own smoke, for his smoke is horrible to inhale, and inhale it you
must. And not only that, but you must live in it for the time. It has an
unspeakable wild Hindu odor about it, such as may lurk in the vicinity of
funeral ps. It smells like the left wing of the day of judgment. It is an
argument for the pit.
By midnight the works were in full operation. We were clear from the
carcass. Sail had been made. The wind was freshening. The wild ocean darkness
was intense. But that darkness was licked up by the fierce flames which at
intervals forked forth from the flu and illuminated every lofty rope in
the rigging as with the famed Greek fire. The burning ship drove on as if
remorselessly commissioned to some vengeful deed. So the pitch and sulfur
freighted brigs of the bold hydriot Caneras issuing from their midnight
harbors with broad sheets of flame for sails bore down upon the Turkish frigots
and folded them in confflgrations.
The hatch removed from the top of the works now afforded a wide hearth in
front of them. Standing on this were the tartarian shapes of the pagan
harpooners, always the whale ship's stokers. With huge prronged poles, they
pitched hissing masses of blubber into the scalding pots or stirred up the
fires beneath, till the snaky flames darted, curling out of the doors to
catch them by the feet. The smoke rolled away in sullen heaps. To every pitch of
the ship there was a pitch of the boiling oil which seemed all eagerness
to leap into their faces. Opposite the mouth of the works. On the further side
of the wide wooden hearth was the windless. This served for a sea sofa.
Here lounged the watch when not otherwise employed. Looking into the red
heat of the fire till our eyes felt scorched in their heads. Their tawny
features now all be grimed with smoke and sweat. their matted beards and the
contrasting barbaric brilliancancy of their teeth. All these were strangely
revealed in the capriccious emlazings of the works, as they narrated to each
other their unholy adventures, their tales of terror told in words of mirth,
as their univilized laughter forked upwards out of them like the flames from
the furnace. As to and fro in their front the harpooners wildly justiculated
with their huge prronged forks and dippers as the wind howled on and the
sea leaped and the ship groaned and dived and yet steadfastly shot her red
hell further and further into the blackness of the sea in the night and
scornfully champed the white bone in her mouth and viciously spat round her on
all sides. Then the rushing Peekquad, freighted with savages, and laden with
fire, and burning a corpse, and plunging into that blackness of darkness, seemed
the material counterpart of her monomomaniac commander's soul.
So seemed it to me, as I stood at her helm, and for long hours silently guided
the way of this fire ship on the sea.
Wrapped for that interval in darkness myself, I but the better saw the
redness, the madness, the ghastliness of others, the continual sight of the fiend
shapes before me, capering half in smoke and half in fire. These at last begat
kindred visions in my soul, so soon as I began to yield to that unaccountable
drowsiness, whichever would come over me at a midnight helm. But that night in
particular, a strange and ever since inexplicable thing occurred to me,
starting from a brief standing sleep, I was horribly conscious of something
fatally wrong. The jawbone tiller smoked my side, which leaned against it. In my
ears was the low hum of sails just beginning to shake in the wind. I
thought my eyes were open. I was half conscious of putting my fingers to the
lids and mechanically stretching them still further apart. But spite of all
this, I could see no compass before me to steer by. Though it seemed but a
minute since I had been watching the card by the steady binnacle lamp
illuminating it, nothing seemed before me but a jet gloom, now and then made
ghastly by flashes of redness. Uppermost was the impression that whatever swift
rushing thing I stood on, was not so much bound to any haven ahead as rushing
from all havens a stern. A stark, bewildered feeling, as if death came
over me. Convulsively my hands grasped the tiller, but with the crazy conceit
that the tiller was somehow in some enchanted way inverted. "My God, what is
the matter with me?" I thought. Lo, in my brief sleep, I had turned myself
about and was fronting the ship's stern, with my back to her prow and the
compass. In an instant, I faced back just in time to prevent the vessel from
flying up into the wind, and very probably capsizing her. How glad and how
grateful the relief from this unnatural hallucination of the night and the fatal
contingency of being brought by the lee.
Look not too long in the face of fire, oh man. Never dream with thy hand on the
helm. Turn not thy back to the compass, except the first hint of the hitching
tiller. Believe not the artificial fire, when its redness makes all things look
ghastly. Tomorrow in the natural sun the skies will be bright. Those who glared
like devils in the forking flames the mourn will show in far other at least
gentler relief. The glorious golden glad sun the only true lamp. All others but liars.
Nevertheless, the sun hides not Virginia's dismal swamp, nor Rome's
oursided Kagna, nor wide Sahara, nor all the millions of miles of deserts and of
griefs beneath the moon. The sun hides not the ocean, which is the dark side of
this earth, and which is twothirds of this earth. So therefore, that mortal
man who hath more of joy than sorrow in him, that mortal man cannot be true, not
true or undeveloped, with books the same. The truest of all men was the man
of sorrows, and the truest of all books is Solomon's, and Ecclesiastes is the
fine hammered steel of woe. All is vanity. All this willful world hath not
got hold of uncchristian Solomon's wisdom yet. But he who dodges hospitals
and jails and walks fast crossing graveyards and would rather talk of
operas than hell calls kalper young Pascal Rouso poor devils all of sick men
and throughout a carefree lifetime swears by rabbles as passing wise and
therefore jolly. Not that man is fitted to sit down on tombstones and break the
green damp mold with unfathomably wondrous Solomon.
But even Solomon, he says, the man that wanderth out of the way of understanding
shall remain, i.e. even while living in the congregation of the dead. Give not
thyself up then to fire, lest it invert thee, deaden thee, as for the time it
did me. There is a wisdom that is woe, but there is a woe that is madness. And
there is a catskill eagle in some souls that can alike dive down into the
blackest gorges and soar out of them again and become invisible in the sunny
spaces. And even if he forever flies within the gorge, that gorge is in the
mountains, so that even in his lowest swoop, the mountain eagle is still
higher than other birds upon the plane.
even though they soar.